They grew up on the outside of society. They weren't looking
for a fight. They were looking to belong.
The Outsiders is a crime, drama film directed by Francis Ford Coppola.
In 1960s Tulsa, class divisions ignite a violent rivalry between
the working-class Greasers and the privileged Socs.
When a deadly encounter forces two Greasers, Ponyboy and Johnny, to flee, their struggle for survival and
redemption exposes the fragile innocence and enduring bonds of youth on the wrong side of town.
Ponyboy Curtis, played by C. Thomas Howell.
Dallas Winston, played by Matt Dillon.
Johnny Cade, played by Ralph Macchio.
Darrel Curtis, played by Patrick Swayze.
Sodapop Curtis, played by Rob Lowe.
Two-Bit Matthews, played by Emilio Estevez.
The Outsiders is a 1983 American coming-of-age crime drama film
directed by Francis Ford Coppola (billed as Francis Coppola).
The film is an adaptation of the 1967 novel of the same name by S.
Hinton and was released on March 25, 1983, in the United States.
Jo Ellen Misakian, a librarian at Lone Star Elementary School in Fresno, California, and
her students were responsible for inspiring Coppola to make the film.
The film is notable for its ensemble cast including C.
Thomas Howell (who garnered a Young Artist Award), Rob Lowe (in his feature film debut), Emilio Estevez,
Matt Dillon, Tom Cruise, Patrick Swayze, Ralph Macchio, Diane Lane, and Leif Garrett.
In addition, Dillon starred in two more films based on Hinton novels: Tex
(1982), with Estevez; and Coppola's Rumble Fish (1983), with Lane.
Estevez also wrote and starred in the Hinton adaptation That Was Then...
This Is Now (1985).
The film received mostly positive reviews from critics, particularly for its performances, and
performed well at the box office, grossing $25.7 million on a $10 million budget.
Over the years, the film has earned a cult following and has spawned a 1990
sequel television series and a successful 2023 stage musical.
The film explores themes of street gang, based on novel or
book, children's home, coming of age, gang.
The tone is dark and emotional.